<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Petrus Repo]]></title>
  <link href="http://ptrs.fi/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ptrs.fi/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-31T11:15:34+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://ptrs.fi/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Petrus Repo]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Damaging big enterprise attitude]]></title>
    <link href="http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/10/23/damaging-enterprise-attitude/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-23T14:46:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/10/23/damaging-enterprise-attitude</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A vulnerability in Java SE allows a complete Java security sandbox bypass. Nevertheless, Oracle decided to stick to its semi-quarter patch release cycle and promised a security fix in February 2013. That is almost five months from now.</p>

<p><a href="http://seclists.org/fulldisclosure/2012/Oct/155">Adam Gowdiak et al. challenge Oracle</a>: they claim that this particular security fix does not require any integration tests with other Oracle application software, needed only 25 characters to be changed and was implemented within 30 minutes.</p>

<p>The culture of Oracle is damaging. It is not acceptable to delay a critical security fix for almost five months because of an enterprise process of &#8220;semi-quarter patch release schedule&#8221;. Oracle has <a href="http://www.theregister.co.uk/2012/08/30/oracle_knew_about_flaws/">also delayed security fixes before</a>.</p>

<p>It is no coincidence that <a href="http://www.engadget.com/2012/10/18/apple-removes-java-from-osx/">Apple has removed Java browser plugin</a> from all OS X browsers and Java is no longer pre-installed in OS X.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Misleading mobile battery life]]></title>
    <link href="http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/10/22/misleading-mobile-battery-life/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-22T11:32:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/10/22/misleading-mobile-battery-life</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Nowadays it seems irrelevant to ask: &#8220;How long does the battery last in my smartphone?&#8221;</p>

<!-- more-->


<p>iPhone 5 draws much more power than iPhone 4/4S, but <a href="http://www.anandtech.com/show/6330/the-iphone-5-review/12">it completes the same benchmark set much faster</a>. Thus, in a long-term benchmark iPhone 5 has a better battery life than its predecessors, because iPhone 5 is able to go to sleep quicker and therefore reduce its power consumption.</p>

<p>However, since people use their device more if they don&#8217;t need to wait, ie. software is more responsive, the &#8220;battery life&#8221; feels weaker. On the other hand, they were able to achieve more in the same time of usage.</p>

<p>In general, comparing devices only by hardware specs is so last season. The answer to the smartphone&#8217;s battery life question is &#8220;one day&#8221; regardless of the hardware, manufacturer or device model.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Internet had a great day]]></title>
    <link href="http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/10/18/internet-had-a-great-day/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-18T21:26:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/10/18/internet-had-a-great-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Internet on paras paikka, <br>
internet, se on iloinen. <br>
Intternetskus vietät vaikka, <br>
koko päivän kesäisen. <br>
(sävel: <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_detailpage&amp;v=ttUnP84N1Tw#t=35s">Puuhamaa</a>)</p></blockquote>

<p>In English:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.netflix.fi/spotify">Netflix became finally available in Finland</a>.
 <br>Free until the end of the year for Spotify customers.</li>
<li>Beautiful and sexy images from <a href="http://goo.gl/O0lg8">Google data centers</a>.</li>
<li>Meteor.js announced <a href="http://meteor.com/blog/2012/10/18/meteor-050-authentication-user-accounts-new-screencast">a delicious new version</a>.</li>
</ul>


<p>The future is happening right now!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Empirical Study of Zero-Day Attacks]]></title>
    <link href="http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/10/17/empirical-study-of-zero-day-attacks/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-17T17:09:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/10/17/empirical-study-of-zero-day-attacks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Stunning statistics:</p>

<blockquote><p>[..] a typical zero-day attack lasts 312 days on average and that, after vulnerabilities are disclosed publicly, the volume of attacks exploiting them increases by up to 5 orders of magnitude.</p></blockquote>

<!-- more -->


<p>&mdash; Leyla Bilge and Tudor Dumitras: <a href="http://users.ece.cmu.edu/~tdumitra/public_documents/bilge12_zero_day.pdf">Before We Knew It: An Empirical Study of Zero-Day Attacks In The Real World</a>.</p>

<p>Google spends a <a href="http://www.chromium.org/Home/chromium-security/hall-of-fame">mentionable amount of money</a> for paying white-hat hackers to find and report previously unknown security issues. However, <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/andygreenberg/2012/03/23/shopping-for-zero-days-an-price-list-for-hackers-secret-software-exploits/">the prices at the black market are presumably much higher</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The two ways to scale a business]]></title>
    <link href="http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/10/16/the-two-ways-to-scale-a-business/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-16T17:54:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/10/16/the-two-ways-to-scale-a-business</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/two-ways-to-build-a-100-million-business-2012-9">Business Insider</a>:
&#8220;Generally speaking, there are two ways (and only two ways) to scale a
business to hit that $100 million threshold:&#8221;</p>

<!-- more -->


<blockquote><ul>
<li><p>Your business has a high Life Time Value (LTV) per user, giving you
the freedom to spend a significant amount of money in customer
acquisition. High LTV can usually be found in transactional or
subscription businesses.</p></li>
<li><p>Your business has a high viral co-efficient (or perhaps even a
network effect) that lets you amass users cheaply without worrying too
much about the monetization per user or spending money on paid
acquisition.</p></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>High life time value can be found especially in subscriptions to services that solve a persistent problem. For example billing &amp; <a href="http://www.getharvest.com/">Harvest</a>, source code &amp; <a href="http://github.com">Github</a>, hosting &amp; <a href="http://www.heroku.com/">Heroku</a>.</p>

<p>On virality, I think Dropbox&#8217;s recent <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/spacerace">Space Race</a> campaign is ingenious. The original viral aspect of &#8220;invite a new user, get free space&#8221; became drained when basically everybody already had Dropbox. Although Space Race is not as efficient as the invite campaign was at start, it will still be harvesting lots of new users.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Responding to negativity]]></title>
    <link href="http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/10/01/responding-to-negativity/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-01T12:44:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/10/01/responding-to-negativity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dealing against negativity in an argumentative manner will only result in more negativity. It does not even matter whether you are arguing in a positive or a negative manner.</p>

<p><a href="http://blogs.hbr.org/bregman/2012/09/how-to-respond-to-negativity.html">According to Peter Bregman</a>, a much more productive response is to respond negatively <em>with</em> others and positively <em>with</em> them.</p>

<p>The difference is more than semantic.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The iPhone 5 paradox]]></title>
    <link href="http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/09/13/the-iphone-5-paradox/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-13T12:39:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/09/13/the-iphone-5-paradox</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>iPhone 5 is currently the most advanced smartphone and, paradoxically, a <a href="http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2012/09/the-iphone-5-is-boring-and-amazing/">really boring</a> new product announcement. By comparing only the hardware specs even the new Nokia Lumia phones may compete. But the devil is in the software.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Last summer I test-drove Nokia Lumia 800, Samsung Galaxy Nexus and Samsung SII. In general these were all decent smartphones with Lumia having smoother usability than Android, but Android beating Lumia in applications. In the end, I wanted to change back to iPhone from all these devices, mostly because of seamless user experience and superior application ecosystem of iOS.</p>

<p>By looking only at the specs and appearance, I would love Lumia 920. However, I just can&#8217;t get over the fact that Internet Explorer is a crappy mobile browser (too many websites appear as broken) and software in Windows Phone&#8217;s app marketplace lose to their Android and iOS counterparts. Comparingly in Android I always feel wary whether clicking a button will actually do what it looks like since there is no consistent paradigm in the user interface.</p>

<p>It is a trap to run a comparison such as &#8220;iPhone vs. Android&#8221;. It&#8217;s like comparing oranges and apple juice. Anrdoid is an ingredient for juice (an operating system) and iPhone is the juice (a mobile phone). Whenever you encounter a comparison between eg. iPhone and Samsung Galaxy S3, you should ask yourself whether you are thinking the phone as a whole (iOS/Android operating system, app ecosystem, the device hardware) or only the cold numbers in a technical spec sheet.</p>

<p>If I wasn&#8217;t so used to the latte of Apple&#8217;s baristas, the regular coffee of Android cafeteria would taste quite good.</p>

<p>Edit: iPhone 5 pre-order <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2012/09/14/iphone-5-pre-order-sells-out-20x-faster-than-4-and-4s-further-highlighting-apples-dominance/">sells out 20 times faster than 4 and 4S</a>, but <a href="http://pandodaily.com/2012/09/13/yesterday-marked-the-beginning-of-the-end-of-apples-dominance-unless/">Apple will soon need to revolutionize in a new industry</a> (eg. televisions) since the mobile revolution has stabilized down to evolution.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://salainen.asia/images/iphone-evolution.jpg" title="Photo from the internets" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How-to use web fonts: vol. 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/08/07/how-to-use-web-fonts-vol-1/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-07T20:56:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/08/07/how-to-use-web-fonts-vol-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>HTML5 web fonts are awesome! On the web, it was previously only possible to use fonts already installed on the user-agent&#8217;s operating system. No more! Since I had not yet actually embedded any web fonts myself, I stumbled upon some problems. This post shares my advice that I got from the internets.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>The Big Picture</h1>

<ol>
<li>You need the actual <a href="http://www.google.com/webfonts/">font data</a>.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.adobe.com/aboutadobe/antipiracy/ff_faq.html">You need a license</a> to use the font.</li>
<li>The font data may be embedded inside a CSS file or linked from a font file.</li>
<li>If you are viewing a local file, you may not link the font outside your local filesystem.</li>
</ol>


<h1>Details</h1>

<p>You may either link the font file or embed it inside your CSS file. Requesting many external downloads will slow down the load time of your page. Therefore it is preferred trying not to add too many references to external resources and consider embedding the fonts inside a common CSS file. For example:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;link href='http://ptrs.fi/style/fonts.css' rel='stylesheet' type='text/css'&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>The embedded fonts are encoded in Base64 format. I found <a href="http://base64fonts.com/">a handy service</a> which does the formatting: you only need to upload the font file. (They also get a copy of all the submitted fonts. Clever way to collect them..)</p>

<p>The embedded font inside the CSS file looks like the following:</p>

<pre><code>@font-face {
  font-family: 'MinionPro';
  src: url(data:font/OpenType;charset=utf-8;base64,[...font data...]) format('OpenType');
  font-weight: normal;
  font-style: normal;
}
</code></pre>

<p>The font may also be linked as follows.</p>

<pre><code>@font-face {
  font-family: 'MinionPro';
  src: url('/style/fonts/minion-pro.ttf');
}
</code></pre>

<p>A good place to find free fonts is <a href="http://www.google.com/webfonts/">Google Web Fonts</a>. Most of fonts require a commercial license. However, you may have a right to use some fonts if you own an applicable software licence. <a href="http://www.adobe.com/aboutadobe/antipiracy/ff_faq.html">Unauthorized copying of fonts</a> is against most copyrights, so you should check the licenses carefully for commercial use.</p>

<p>Note that if you are viewing your page directly from a local file, the browser&#8217;s same-origin policy does not allow linking files outside your local file system. That is, for example Google Web Fonts may not work without using a local webserver.</p>

<p>Summary: Web will get a facelift since layouts are no longer restricted to Helvetica, Verdana, Lucida &amp; co!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't feel ashamed to apologize]]></title>
    <link href="http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/07/20/dont-feel-ashamed-to-apologize/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-20T12:56:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/07/20/dont-feel-ashamed-to-apologize</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The author of <a href="http://bootstrappingdesign.com/">Bootstrapping Design</a> self-published his book, and therefore, he kept control over how the sales and customer relations should be handled. The author, Jarrod Drysdale, wrote a <a href="http://blog.studiofellow.com/2012/05/31/30k-ebook-sales-in-2-months/">retrospective about the lessons learned</a>. One particular thought got my attention:</p>

<!-- more -->


<blockquote><p>I made an honest mistake after launch. The coupon I had promised everyone on my mailing list expired before I said it would.</p>

<p>I reactivated the coupon, extended the expiration by an extra week, and sent an email to the list apologizing. This apology email drove about $1,200 in sales. Other newsletters have not converted quite so well.</p></blockquote>

<p>In other words: tell your customers that you screwed up and proactively offer a refund, coupon or something nice. The gesture will likely pay itself back.</p>

<p>PS. The price of $39 is high for an ebook, but the goal was <a href="http://blog.asmartbear.com/higher-pricing.html">more money from fewer sales</a>. When targetted to the right audience, the price does not feel too much even though the book&#8217;s font-size is large, almost every other page has pictures and the content fits in 150 pages. The author did something right since the book collected a revenue of $30,000 in two months.</p>

<p>If I would ever write a book, I would <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2012/01/28/why-every-entrepreneur-should-self-publish-a-book/">self-publish it</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Details from Lumia 800 test drive]]></title>
    <link href="http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/06/19/details-from-lumia-800-test-drive/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-19T10:15:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/06/19/details-from-lumia-800-test-drive</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://salainen.asia/images/lumia-gmail-small.jpg" width="260" height="506" title="Gmail in Lumia 800 with Internet Explorer" ></p>

<p>In addition to the TOP-3 problems from my Lumia 800 Test Drvice, I collected a set of details. These issues are not actual deal killers, but since there are a lot of the small issues, the general usability is degraded.</p>

<p>These details won&#8217;t make a difference without the bigger picture, so please read <a href="http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/06/18/nokia-lumia-800-test-drive/">the list of TOP-3 problems
</a> first.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>First impressions with Lumia</h2>

<ul>
<li>Design of the physical device feels especially comfortable in your hand.</li>
<li>Scrolling and graphical effects are fluent, display feels bright.</li>
<li>Setup of synchronization for contacts and (one) calendar was easy! (However, <a href="http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/06/18/nokia-lumia-800-test-drive/">it wasn&#8217;t working properly.</a>)</li>
<li>Some web pages look weird</li>
<li>This is my first phone since 2005 which displays text messages from SIM card. I did not remember I even had those. I was surprised to see messages from an ex-girlfriend. :)  In the old times text messages were stored in the SIM card and there was a limit of keeping max 20  messages at once.</li>
<li>This is my first Nokia where the clock is easy to access when the keypad is locked.</li>
<li>Lumia has about the same physical size, dimensions and weight than an iPhone.</li>
<li>Everything in the UI seems to be scrollable in any direction (up-down &amp; left-right).</li>
<li>There is no way to take a screenshot!</li>
<li>Software update is found instantly after the first boot, but updating requires a computer and a Microsoft&#8217;s Zune software. Nokia&#8217;s download link first sent me a Windows version so I needed to specifically search for the OS X version.</li>
<li>&#8220;Battery saver&#8221; is a good feature which is not available in iPhone. When needed, as a battery saver I have switched off 3G and cellular data. However, new versions of iOS have disabled switching off the 3G network.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Features I would like to have:</h2>

<h3>Screen resolution comparable to a Retina display.</h3>

<p>The Lumia display is pretty sharp, but on the other hand, the font in native applications is usually fairly large. Sharpness of the display is needed in web browsing when text in non-mobile optimized websites is usually quite small. You will see the difference if you open any non-mobile optimized site (which you will often get with Internet Explorer) and compare it between Lumia&#8217;s AMOLED and iPhone&#8217;s Retina display. The small text is readable and very sharp with iPhone&#8217;s Retina display but blurry in Lumia.</p>

<h3>Internet tethering.</h3>

<p>This is fundamental when you take your laptop and want to work outside your office. This could be compensated with a 3G USB-modem. However, I have used the iOS Personal Hotspot feature in so many surprising situations that I guess I would never have a separate USB dongle with me should I need an ad-hoc internet connection.</p>

<p>There is a rumor that tethering will come available by a software update, but it was not available yet as of June 2012.</p>

<h3>Software Updates for the Windows Operating System</h3>

<p>Neither Microsoft nor Nokia has stated that current Lumia devices (running WP7) will get an update to WP8 which is about to be released during the autumn 2012. Rumours are actually quite the opposite: <a href="http://www.zdnet.com/blog/microsoft/reading-between-the-lines-office-on-ipad-windows-phone-upgrades/12101">Current Lumia devices might never get an update to WP8.</a></p>

<p>In contrast, iOS devices have gotten updates to the new operating system. iPhone 4 (released in 2010 with iOS 4) will get an update to iOS6, and probably even iPhone 3GS will work with iOS 6.</p>

<h3>Wireless streaming of music (such as Airplay).</h3>

<p>I stream music wirelessly from Spotify to Airport Express which is plugged into my stereos. iOS devices support that natively, but on the desktop, I need to use a third-party application called Airfoil. There could be a third-party application for Windows Phone which could do the same. However, I don&#8217;t know if it&#8217;s technically possible because of application sandboxing or security restrictions.</p>

<p>During the test it became clear that I have already invested in different pieces of Apple hardware for several years.</p>

<h3>MMS messages.</h3>

<p>I could&#8217;t receive MMS messages. I don&#8217;t know why, but they just don&#8217;t load. When I receive a new MMS, Lumia displays a link &#8220;Get media content now&#8221;. When I click it, Lumia tells me it is loading the content, but then it just fails silently, does not display any error message and I don&#8217;t see the MMS message. A Google search revealed that this is a common problem.</p>

<h3>Online backups.</h3>

<p>I don&#8217;t need to worry losing my photos should I lose my iPhone. Lumia must be backupped manually, which I would probably remember to do once a month &#8211; maybe.</p>

<h2>Minor Details</h2>

<h3>If you have used Apple&#8217;s iMessages before..</h3>

<p>If you have ever activated iMessages on your iOS device, you need to explicitly disable iMessages. Otherwise your friends with iPhones, in the worst case, can&#8217;t send you text messages at all. In a happy case or there is only a long delay. I did not run statistics, but there were several messages I never actually received because friends&#8217; iPhone did not fallback from iMessage to SMS.</p>

<p>The technical reason seems to be that iPhone tries to send you iMessage first, and it fallbacks to regular SMS only after a significant delay. According to my experience, most text messages from friends using iPhone couldn&#8217;t get through at all before I disabled iMessages completely. This might have something to do with the fact that I had a multi-sim in my iPhone which was connected to the network with the same phone number than Lumia. Lumia had the primary sim card for SMS messages, though.</p>

<p>(iMessage is Apple&#8217;s instant messaging system which works like SMS but without usage costs).</p>

<h3>Hardware and the Physical Device</h3>

<!-- - Although Lumia's display (800x480) loses to iPhone's retina (960x640) in sharpness, Lumia's picture quality is still very good. - Native applications usually have a large font which makes the display feel small. The display doesn't usually show lots of text at once, which means that you need to scroll the views more often than with a sharper display.
-->


<!-- - I was not used to hardware buttons (back, search, camera). -->


<p>There is no hardware button for silencing the ringer volume. You need to click lock-screen button and then hold down the volume button until it&#8217;s value is 0/20. To get ringer back, you need to hold the button until it&#8217;s value is XX/20. Unless you pay attention to this, the ringer volume will usually always reach the maximum (20/20) &#8211; there is no way to configure presets or have a fast-access silencer for ringer volume.</p>

<p>The hardware buttons for volume up/volume down are not easily accessible during call. I accidentally tried to lower the volume several times from the camera button since it feels the same as the adjacent camera button. I was never sure if I had the right button, sometimes I accidentally muted the whole call since I did not hear the difference in the volume and I was not sure whether I was pressing the camera button.</p>

<p>The hardware search button is reserved for a global internet search using Bing. When an application provides a search function, there is a software button which usually looks the same as the hardware button. Some applications place the software search button right on top of the hardware search button, which looks weird.</p>

<p>The battery lasts about the same amount of time as iPhone &#8211; both phones need to be charged every night if you use them for anything. During the test iPhone&#8217;s standby time surprised me, it was five days in my bag without a recharge (because I did not use it).</p>

<!-- Measurements
- Weight: lumia 142g (iphone 137g)
- paksuus lumia 12mm (iphone 9mm)
- koko lumia 61x116x12 mm (iphone 58x114x9mm). lumia 900:ssa 800x400, jää myös retinasta
- reso 800x480, 252 PPI (iphone 640x960, 329 PPI)
 -->


<h3>Camera</h3>

<p>You can start the camera application from the hardware button even if your phone is locked. This may be disabled, but then you don&#8217;t have a camera shortcut. I kept this enabled, but somehow I accidentally launched the camera application several times only by holding the device in my hand.</p>

<p>For an accidental camera launch to happen, the lock button must be pressed once before the camera button is pressed. But this is easy to do by accident because both buttons are physical and both are located on the same side of the phone. (For the record, iOS camera shortcut is from a software button which does not react in your pocket.)</p>

<h3>User Interface in General</h3>

<p>Moving the cursor on the screen is a daunting task. iOS displays a small spyglass which helps you to place the cursor the same way as you select the place for the cursor by clicking. Lumia displays a help cursor, but moving it feels unintuitive. You need to try this by yourself to understand.</p>

<p>Many applications use 1/4 of the screen for a header which is placed on top of the screen (eg. Facebook). This makes the screen appear tight, that is, the header eats the space which could be used for displaying the actual content.</p>

<p>Instead of a context aware software back button, there is a swipe left/right navigation system. For example in Evernote you navigate by swiping left from Notes to Notebooks. In the iOS version, you navigate back to Notebooks from a software back button. However, in Lumia, if you click hardware back button it exists the application instead of going back to &#8220;Notebooks&#8221; from &#8220;Notes&#8221;. Maybe application developers have not yet understood the &#8220;Metro Way&#8221; of UI design, but currently many WP applications have confusing navigation.</p>

<p>You can&#8217;t see when an application is synchronizing. I don&#8217;t know whether WP7 applications can handle their sync tasks in the background. Therefore I am not confident to lock the screen and put the phone in my pocket before I know that the synchronization is done. On the other hand, my calendar never got synchronized reliably so what can you do. (When an iOS app synchronizes, a spinner is displayed next to the carrier information on top of the screen.)</p>

<p>Sometimes touch events are interpreted incorrectly. For example, when scrolling downwards, the downward movement stops and the screen gets scrolled a little bit upwards. That is, when I lift my finger from the screen, a swipe-up event is registered although I did not want to swipe up. This happened very often when I browsed Facebook laying on bed or a sofa. This has not happened to me on iOS.</p>

<h3>Calendar (in addition to the high priority issues)</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>Default reminder!!! I don&#8217;t want to set any reminders, but all new calendar events will get a reminder set 15 minutes before the event. You need to disable these one-by-one, there is no default setting you could change. This is annoying, since I don&#8217;t want any calendar beebs at all.</p></li>
<li><p>Moving between dates feels cumbersome. You can&#8217;t get to next/previous day by swiping left/right, instead you need to scroll a longer listing up/down. This feels dumb if you want move several days at once.</p></li>
<li><p>Synchronization issues and lack of delegated calendars, see top of this post.</p></li>
<li><p>There is no weekly view, only daily and monthly views. It is hard to get an overview of a whole week.</p></li>
<li><p>Calendar shows current events in lock screen. This cannot be disabled. I did not like this feature at all, as I don&#8217;t like text message previews in lock screen either.</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Evernote</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>You need to choose &#8220;edit&#8221; two times and then you need to save your text two times. Why?</p></li>
<li><p>When you write text which is longer than available space, your newly-written text goes under the keyboard. Has anybody actually written anything longer than &#8220;asdfasdf&#8221; in the WP app?</p></li>
<li><p>You can&#8217;t get an empty line between text paragraph. There is just no way. Your text will be a one long paragraph.</p></li>
<li><p>Application gets often jammed if I switch between Internet Explorer and Evernote (e.g. when reading a web page and writing a memo at the same time).</p></li>
<li><p>Somehow Evernote doubled the contents of one note. Another synchronization issue.</p></li>
<li><p>These are clear and very-easy-to-spot kind of bugs which make me wonder whether anybody actually uses Evernote on a Windows Phone.</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Nokia Transit</h3>

<p>In Helsinki public transport you can&#8217;t use Nokia Transit for: &#8220;Leave on the third stop after Mannerheimintie.&#8221; You can&#8217;t view the bus route, you can only view the walking routes. This means that you don&#8217;t know which bus stops in the map are for your bus in the suggested route. Nokia Transit supports several cities around the world, but in Helsinki, it loses brightly for ReittiGPS (an iOS app for Helsinki).</p>

<p>I understand that Nokia wants to be international and stuff, but they have blasted for years how they are a Finnish company. Therefore I would have expected that the Finnish Flagship of Navigation would do well in their home ground.</p>

<h3>Youtube</h3>

<p>You can&#8217;t freely move the position in a video. The app provides arrow buttons which will skip 30 seconds per click. How to skip 15 seconds?</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>The appearance of Lumia is amiable, the external design of the device feels enjoyable, but the software is full of small issues which degrade usability. The Windows Phone as a platform seems to be some years behind its rivals iOS and Android. The question remains: Why would someone use the same amount of money (~ 400 €) to buy a Lumia instead of an Android? Even the three-year-old iPhone 3GS (370 €) seems a viable choice instead of Lumia 800.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nokia Lumia 800 test drive]]></title>
    <link href="http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/06/18/nokia-lumia-800-test-drive/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-18T17:10:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/06/18/nokia-lumia-800-test-drive</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I took a new Lumia 800 to a test for two weeks. During this period I used Lumia 800 as my primary phone. I wanted to answer the following question:</p>

<blockquote><p>If I prefer an iPhone to a Lumia, what are the three most important problems for me in Lumia 800?</p></blockquote>

<p><img class="right" src="http://salainen.asia/images/lumia-steve-small.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>My first two mobile phones were Nokia 3110 and 6110. That was when Nokia still ruled in the mobiles! My very last Nokia was a Symbian E75 smartphone which I had in 2009. That Nokia phone already felt quite incompatible with the Internet, so I soon switched to Android. Now I have used an iPhone after the release of iPhone 4 in 2010.</p>

<p>Since I live in Finland, I&#8217;m interested in the whereabouts of Nokia. Only two days ago <a href="http://yle.fi/uutiset/nokia_vahentaa_suomesta_3_700/6180987">Nokia laid out 3700 employees in Finland</a> (the biggest layoff in Finnish history) and announced shutdown of significant factories in Finland and Germany. <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2012/06/15/samsung-apple-walk-away-with-90-percent-of-smartphone-profits-in-q1-2012-says-abi-research/">According to TechCrunch</a> and senior ABI analyst Michael Morgan, “at this point in the year, Nokia will have to grow its Windows Phone business 5000% in 2012 just to offset its declines in Symbian shipments.” So Lumia should better kick some ass! (And have at least the following TOP-3 problems solved.)</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Internet already has a wide selection of <a href="http://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2012/04/the-nokia-lumia-900-a-good-phone-at-a-great-price-that-you-probably-shouldnt-buy/">reviews</a> and <a href="https://www.google.fi/search?q=Lumia+vs+iPhone+4">Lumia vs iPhone 4</a> articles. This is not one of them. Instead, I merely wanted to write down my own thoughts so I can refer to them later when I will test the next generation Lumias with Windows 8.</p>

<h2>TOP-3 Problems</h2>

<p>My TOP-3 of Problems are mostly related to Windows Phone as a platform. I don&#8217;t know how much fixing these is in the hands of Microsoft, and how much Nokia could do about them. I would really want to see a serious third player in the market mobile platforms which is currently dominated by iOS and Android. I wish Nokia will not only end up as Microsoft&#8217;s bitch, but have a stand on the issues regarding its very own future.</p>

<h3>1. Calendar &amp; Contacts: Unreliable synchronization.</h3>

<p>Synchronization of calendar and contacts with Google was easy to setup, but Lumia&#8217;s synchronization features cannot be trusted at all. Sync between Google Calendear and Lumia&#8217;s calendar cannot be manually forced and there is no way to be sure that your appointments have been synced with Google &#8211; often they are not.</p>

<p>During the first days of usage this seemed to be just a little hiccup, but soon it became clear that Lumia is never fully synchronized with Google Calendar. Whenever I needed to view my calendar, I picked up my iPhone since I could not trust Lumia showing all my appointments.</p>

<p>Delegated calendars are not supported either. In addition to my personal calendar, I need my work calendar and it is also handy that my wife has given me read access to her calendar. Both are delegated to my personal Google account. Lumia supports only the one primary calendar of a Google account &#8211; there is no way to access delegated calendars. <a href="http://support.google.com/mobile/bin/answer.py?hl=en&amp;answer=139206">Delegated calendars need some setup</a> for iPhone, but it seems that Lumia is out of luck with this one.</p>

<p>Another problem are the contacts in Lumia&#8217;s address book. When I create a new contact in &#8220;Google directory&#8221;, the contact gets created in Lumia, but it will not be propagated immediately to Google. Also, new contacts created in Google are not visible in Lumia, and there is no way to manually initiate the synchronization. This feels awkward, since the Lumia is constantly unsynchronized and I ended up with contacts and calendar data which are only available locally in Lumia.</p>

<h3>2. Application ecosystem: Apps feel immature.</h3>

<p>At the moment it seems that most mobile applications launch first with a polished iOS app, and an Android app follows as a little brother. For the time being many popular or novelty applications are not available in Windows Phone&#8217;s Marketplace. This will probably change after the Windows Phone platform matures, but for the time being many third party Windows Phone applications seem to have more bugs than their iOS versions.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.evernote.com">Evernote</a> is probably the one third-party application I use the most on iPhone. However, the Windows Phone version has several issues which degrade its usability. Some of them are so clear (and annoying), that I wondered if anyone actually uses Evernote on a Windows Phone. Description of the bugs is at the end of this post.</p>

<p>The need for Facebook Messenger surprised me. I had not realized the volume of instant messages which are sent to me via Facebook. Whenever I grabbed my iPhone, FB Messenger told me I have new messages. I did I know about them while using Lumia because I did not regularly check my Facebook account. On iPhone, instant messages from FB Messger are delivered to you in the same way as SMS text messages, so you don&#8217;t need to open the Facebook application in order to check messages.</p>

<p>This problem boils down to a classical dilemma: A platform needs users to get applications, but on the other hand the platform needs applications to get users.</p>

<h3>3. Internet Explorer: Incompatibility issues.</h3>

<p>Lumia&#8217;s browser blows in comparison to Webkit based browsers in Android and iOS. Some web pages look only visually broken, but some pages don&#8217;t work at all. Some sites show you a mobile version from the Symbian dark-ages (even Gmail) or show you the desktop site even though a mobile site is available. There is no copy paste, Javascript based pages feel slower than with Webkit and I couldn&#8217;t have IE to save passwords.</p>

<p>Knowing the past history of Internet Explorer, these problems are not about to change, unless developers actually start testing their web site with a Windows Phone. And that requires that there are much more Windows Phone users in order for developers to care.</p>

<p>Side note: I probably could get used to Bing as the Lumia&#8217;s default search engine &#8212; if only the browser was better.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>Lumia 800 is a decent smartphone, but it is two or three years behind its rivals. The physical form and design of the device feels excellent and the gadget looks beautiful. I know people who even <em>love</em> their Lumia, however, Lumia has usually been the first smartphone for them.</p>

<p>I liked the overall experience, but Lumia 800 gave me the same feeling of incompleteness which I had with Android-based Samsung Spica in 2010. My goal was to find out what exactly is the problem for <strong>me</strong> to use the Lumia 800 instead of an iPhone 4. In addition to the TOP-3 problems described above, I also collected <a href="http://ptrs.fi/blog/2012/06/19/details-from-lumia-800-test-drive/">details from the test drive</a>. Most of them are personal opinions which won&#8217;t make a difference for me until the TOP-3 problems listed in this post are gone.</p>

<p>With these issues, Lumia will not help <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2012/06/15/samsung-apple-walk-away-with-90-percent-of-smartphone-profits-in-q1-2012-says-abi-research/">Nokia to grow its sales by 5000% this year</a>. Lumia is a good choice for people who don&#8217;t want much from their smartphone software or who don&#8217;t use much mobile internet. But why would one buy a Lumia 800 for the same price (~400 €) when they can spend the same amount of money for an Android device? Even the three-year-old iPhone 3GS (370 €) seems a viable choice instead of Lumia 800.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
